Guide to the Rice University Board of Trustees, Chairman Bill Barnett records, 1990-2005, bulk 1996-2004 UA 104
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Board of Trustees, Chairman Bill Barnett records
1990-2005
bulk
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Barnett, E. William
UA 104
14 Linear Feet (28 boxes)
These materials reflect the daily business of Rice University Chairman of the Board Bill Barnett, including correspondence, reports, publications and newsclippings. As board chair, Barnett led the strengthening of the university's governance, moving from the two-tiered board to a single-tier board enlarged to 25 trustees. Under his leadership, the board elected a far more diverse group of trustees with representation from all parts of the country; the university amended its charter to allow for the use of debt financing, which led to the largest building and modernization program in the campus's history; and the university's endowment grew from $1.7 billion to $3.4 billion.
14 linear feet (28 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
E. William "Bill" Barnett, former managing partner of the Baker Botts law firm, served as chair of the Rice University Board of Governors 1996 to 2005. Barnett joined the Rice Board of Governors in 1991 as a term member and was elected a trustee in 1994.
As board chair, Barnett led the strengthening of the university's governance, moving from the two-tiered board to a single-tier board enlarged to 25 trustees. Under his leadership, the board elected a far more diverse group of trustees with representation from all parts of the country; the university amended its charter to allow for the use of debt financing, which led to the largest building and modernization program in the campus's history; and the university's endowment grew from $1.7 billion to $3.4 billion.
Barnett succeeded Charles W. Duncan, Jr., who retired after serving as board chair for 14 years. Barnett is also a contributing life member of the Rice Associates, a member of the Rice University Fund Council, and a member of the Friends of Fondren.
Barnett received his B.A. from Rice in 1955 and his LL.B. in 1958 from the University of Texas at Austin. He has led a distinguished career as an attorney and as a civic leader. He is former chairman of the Antitrust Section of the American Bar Association and is a fellow of the American College of Trial Lawyers.
He is past chairman and current board member of the Greater Houston Partnership, past chairman and current board member of Central Houston, Inc. and has served on the board of directors of Texas Commerce Bancshares. He is a trustee of Baylor College of Medicine and a life trustee of the University of Texas Law School Foundation.
Barnett is married to Peggy Mauk Barnett, a 1955 Rice graduate. They have two children, Margaret Ann Barnett Stern and Edward William Barnett, Jr., both of Houston.
The Rice Board of Governors is comprised of seven trustees, eight term governors and four alumni governors. There are also seven trustee emerti and 47 governor advisors.
[Excerpted from Rice University press release,(http://www.media.rice.edu/media) "Barnett Named Chair of Rice Board of Governors", April 11, 1996]
Scope and Contents
These materials reflect the daily business of Rice University Chairman of the Board Bill Barnett, including correspondence, reports, publications and newsclippings. As board chair, Barnett led the strengthening of the university's governance, moving from the two-tiered board to a single-tier board enlarged to 25 trustees. Under his leadership, the board elected a far more diverse group of trustees with representation from all parts of the country; the university amended its charter to allow for the use of debt financing, which led to the largest building and modernization program in the campus's history; and the university's endowment grew from $1.7 billion to $3.4 billion.
Access Restrictions
Access to this material requires permission from the Board of Trustees. Contact the Woodson Research Center for assistance in obtaining permission. Please call 713-348-2586 or e-mail woodson@rice.edu.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This material was transferred to the Woodson Research Center, 2006.
Related Material
Rice University Board of Trustees records, http://www.rice.edu/fondren/woodson/archives/board_trustees.html
Index Terms
Subjects
College trustees; Rice University -- History; Universities and colleges
Subjects (Persons)
Barnett, E. William
- Series I: Administrative Matters, 1996-2004
  - Names and Addresses (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1993-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1996-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative personnel, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personnel: President's Office, Malcolm Gillis, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personnel: Provost, David Auston, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personnel: VP Advancement, Kathryn Costello, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personnel: General Counsel, Shirley Redwine, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personnel: Dean, Shepherd School of Music, Michael Hammond, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personnel: Compensation survey, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personnel: "Select Universities Survey, 1996-1997" regarding executive compensation (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personnel: Salary and benefit matters, 1996-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Personnel: Report of the Ad-Hoc Faculty Advisory Committee on Retirement, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personnel: Organized Materials: Fact Sheet, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personnel: Data regarding other schools, 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personnel: Foundations, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personnel: Materials regarding searches, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - President's Letters and Reports, 1996-2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty matters, 1999-2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Admissions, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Admissions: Enrollment Retreat Briefing Book, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - College system, 1997, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Outside audits of academic units, 1997, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Graduate housing, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - U.S. News and World Report, 1997-2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bremen (International University of Bremen, 1997-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - UK Joint Venture, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minority matters, 1998-2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Parking, 1991, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Santa Fe venture, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - KTRU radio, 1990, 2000-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series II: Board materials, 1996-2005
  - 1996-2004
    - General, 1996-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Trustees material, 1996-2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Trustees material, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Board meetings, 1992-2002 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Governors materials, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Materials regarding nominations, 1996-2004 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Materials regarding nominations, binder (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Materials regarding Board restructuring, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Charters and by-laws materials, 1994-2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Board Secretary, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Conflict of Interest Policy, 1996-2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Alumni Governor Elections, 1997, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Campus climate for women, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Search committees, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1996-2005
    - Academic Affairs, 1996-2002 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Audit, 1994-2004 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Advisory Boards, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Board Committees - General, 1995-2002 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Building and Grounds, 1994-2004 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Building and Grounds, Part II, 1994-2004 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Financial Affairs, 1991-1998 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - University Advancement, 1996-2002 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Rice University Fund Council (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Rice University Athletics, 2003-2005 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Compensation, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Compensation, Part II, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Compensation Part III, 1998-2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Compensation Committee, 1996-2000 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Series III: Financial Affairs, 1996-2005
  - Financial Affairs - General, 1996-2002 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Budget Matters, 1996-2005 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Endowment, 1996-2002 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Investment Managers, 1995-2000 (Box not specified, Folder 4)
  - Audit Materials, 1996-2002 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Tuition Matters, 1996-2002 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Financing Alternatives, 1998-2001 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Investment Subcommittees, 1994-1999 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Licensing Royalties, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Start Up Companies, 2000-2001 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Rice-Land Lumber Company, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Legal Matters, 1994-2004
  - Legal Matters - General, 1996-2001 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Current Litigation, 1996-1998 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Current Non-Litigation Matters, 1996-2004 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Charter Amendments, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Analysis of Charter Amendment, 1986-1998 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Barnett, 1996-1999 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative Action, 1996-1999 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Title IX, 1993-1996 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Code of Student Conduct, 1991-2002 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Tenure, 1996-1999 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Conflict of Interest, 1991-2002 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Estate Matters, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - I.P. Protection Program, 1994-1999 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Same sex benefits, 1997-1999 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Thresher Related, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Prohibition Debt, 1997-1998 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Property Taxes, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Honor Council, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Series V: Athletics, 1990-2004
  - Athletics - General, 1990-2004 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Athletics - General, Part II, 1990-2004 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Athletics - General, Part III, 1990-2004 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Athletics - General, Part IV, 1990-2004 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, Part II, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, Part III, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, 2003 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, Part II, 2003 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, Part III, 2003 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Report on Athletics, Part IV, 2003 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Athletics Committee - Materials for Consultants, 2002-2003 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Financial Information, 1997-2000 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Data re other schools, 1992-2001 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - WAC Matters, 1996-2000 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Neighborhood Concerns, 1995-1999 (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Admissions, 1996-2003
  - Admissions - General, 1996-2003 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Survey Information, 1996-2001 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Student Matters, 1997-2003 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Promotional Materials, 1998-2003 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Minority Students, 2000-2003 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Series VII: Development Matters, 1996-2004
  - Developmental Matters - General, 1996-2003 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Computational Engineering, 1996-2002 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Nanotechnology, 1996-2002 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Capital Campaign Planning, 1996-2001 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Capital Campaign Planning, Part II, 1996-2001 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Fundraising, 1997-1999 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Planned Giving, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - RUFC, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Associates, 1996-1998 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Wiess House, 1997-2003 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Foundations, 1998-2002 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Center for Study of Religious Tolerance, 2004 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Malcolm Gillis University Chair, 2004 (Box 22, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: External Affairs, 1996-2004
  - External Affairs - General, 1996-2002 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Public Relations, 1996-2003 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Beyond the Hedges - Planning, 1999-2004 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Baylor Medical School, 1996-2002 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Flood Project, 2000-2001 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - METRO, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Southeast Texas Bio Park, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Rice Centennial, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Rice/Monterrey Tech Academic Visit, April 2, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - BioHouston, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Texas Medical Center (TMC), 2003 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - University/Main, 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - English Joint Venture, 2002 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Series IX: Strategic Planning, 1994-2002
  - Strategic Planning - General, 1994-1998 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Strategic Planning - General, Part II, 1994-1998 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Strategic Planning Report, 1996-1999 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Jones School Report, 1996-1998 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Leadership Rice, 1997-1999 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Campus Planning, 1999-2002 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Series X: Campus issues, 1996-2003
  - Historical Materials, 1996-2003 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Genome Grant, 1996-2003 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Baker Institute - General, 1993-2003 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Baker Institute - General, Part II, 1993-2003 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Baker Search Committee, 1991-1994 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Institutional Materials - General, 1996-2001 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Student Surveys, 1996-2003 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Leadership Rice, 1998-2000 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Historical Materials, 1995-1998 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Association of Rice Alumni, 1999-2000 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Library, 1995-2000 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Information Technology, 1995-2001 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Jesse H. Jones Graduate School, 1996-2002 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Jones School - RATE (Rice Alliance for Technology and Entrepreneurship), 1999-2001 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Capital Campaign - General, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Undergraduate Packet, 1995-1996 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Architect Selection, 1997 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Presidential Search Committee, 2003 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Presidential Search Committee, Part I, 2003 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Items, 2004 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Presidential Transition (Leebron), 2003 (Box 28, Folder 4)